<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2022 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="oheger@apache.org">Oliver Heger</author>
    <title>Custom style sheets in JGuiraffe JavaFX applications</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Using Custom Style Sheets">
  <p>
    JavaFX's support for Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) enables flexible and
    powerful styling capabilities for user interfaces. By providing custom
    style sheet files that override some or all of the default style classes,
    it is possible to adapt a whole application using special themes.
  </p>
  <p>
    <em>JGUIraffe</em> supports the integration of an arbitrary number of
    custom style sheet files. In JavaFX css files are added to
    <code>Scene</code> objects. The component responsible for the creation of
    <code>Scene</code> objects in <em>JGUIraffe</em> JavaFX applications is
    <code><a href="scaladocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/platform/javafx/builder/window/JavaFxWindowManager.html">
    JavaFxWindowManager</a></code>, the JavaFX-specific implementation of the
    <code><a href="../../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/WindowManager.html">
    WindowManager</a></code> interface. So this is the starting point for
    customizing style sheets.
  </p>
  <p>
    <code>JavaFxWindowManager</code> expects an instance of the
    <code><a href="scaladocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/platform/javafx/builder/window/StyleSheetProvider.html">
    StyleSheetProvider</a></code> class to be passed to its constructor. As the
    name implies, this class is capable of managing style sheets - to be more
    precise: a set of string URLs pointing to such files. This is exactly the
    format accepted by a <code>Scene</code>. In order to make custom style
    sheets available to JavaFX, an application has to create a
    <code>StyleSheetProvider</code> object and initialize it accordingly.
  </p>
  <p>
    As usual, the major part of the configuration of a <em>JGUIraffe</em>
    application is done via the <a href="../../userguide/dibuilder.html">dependency
    injection framework</a>. The default beans definition file shipped with the
    JavaFX integration of <em>JGUIraffe</em> contains bean declarations for both
    the window manager and the style sheet provider. An application can define
    its own bean definition file in which it overrides beans of the framework.
    For the purpose of adding specific style sheets the bean with the name
    <em>jguiraffe.styleSheetProvider</em> has to be overridden. This can be
    done by declaring a bean of class
    <code>net.sf.jguiraffe.gui.platform.javafx.builder.window.StyleSheetProvider</code>
    and passing a comma-separated list of string URLs for the style sheet files to
    the constructor.
  </p>
  <p>
    Situation is a bit more complicated because these URLs have to be generated
    first. Typically, custom style sheets are shipped as resources on the
    class path of an application. To make sure that they are correctly found by
    JavaFX, they have to be transformed into URLs. Fortunately, the dependency
    injection tag library offers a tag for exactly this purpose:
    <a href="../../userguide/dibuilder.html#Access_to_class_path_resources">&lt;resource&gt;</a>.
    Using this tag, a number of resource names representing css files can be
    resolved to string URLs, concatenated, and assigned to a Jelly variable.
    This variable can then be referenced in the declaration of the style sheet
    provider bean. This is demonstrated in the following example. We assume that
    two style sheet files, <em>standard.css</em>, and <em>special.css</em> are
    to be added:
  </p>
<source><![CDATA[
<j:jelly xmlns:j="jelly:core" xmlns:di="diBuilder" xmlns:f="formBuilder"
  xmlns:a="actionBuilder" xmlns:w="windowBuilder">
  <di:resource resource="standard.css" var="styleSheets"/>
  <di:resource resource="special.css" var="styleSheets" delimiter=","/>

  <di:bean name="jguiraffe.styleSheetProvider"
    beanClassName="net.sf.jguiraffe.gui.platform.javafx.builder.window.StyleSheetProvider">
    <di:constructor>
      <di:param value="${styleSheets}"/>
    </di:constructor>
  </di:bean>
</j:jelly>]]></source>
  <p>
    This bean definition file (let's assume it is called
    <code>applicationbeans.jelly</code>) can be executed automatically at
    application start up as described in the sub section
    <a href="../../userguide/application.html#Hooks">Hooks</a>. Basically, it
    has to be listed in the <em>&lt;beandefinitions&gt;</em> section of the
    application's main configuration file <code>framework-config.xml</code>:
  </p>
<source><![CDATA[
<config>
  <framework>
    <builder>
      <mainScript>main.jelly</mainScript>
      <beandefinitions>
        <beandefinition>classpath:applicationbeans.jelly</beandefinition>
      </beandefinitions>
      ...
    </builder>
    ...
]]></source>
  <p>
    That's it! The style sheet classes defined in the two css files are now
    available.
  </p>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
