<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2014 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: validators.xml 205 2012-01-29 18:29:57Z oheger $ -->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Transformers and Validators</title>
  <author email="oheger@users.sourceforge.net">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Transformers and Validators">
  <p>
    A library that provides support for input forms also has to deal with the
    data entered by the user:
    <ul>
    <li>The input fields of the form have to be validated to ensure that the
    user has entered correct data.</li>
    <li>Data type conversion may also be required. Input fields used within
    forms (e.g. plain text input fields) usually store their context as strings
    only and are not aware of any specific data type. For instance, if an input
    field is used for entering a date, it contains only a text representation
    of a valid date. To provide the application with meaningful data this text
    representation has to be converted to a <code>java.util.Date</code> object.
    </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    In the <em>JGUIraffe</em> library this topic is covered by so-called
    <code>Validator</code> and <code>Transformer</code> classes, which are
    located in the <code>net.sf.jguiraffe.transform</code> package. In the
    following sub sections we discuss their usage.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Fundamental interfaces">
  <p>
    The fundamental interfaces in the <code>tranform</code> packages are
    <code>Validator</code> and <code>Transformer</code>.
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/Validator.html">Validator</a></code>
    is responsible for validation of data entered by the user. The interface
    defines a single method with the following signature:
    <source><![CDATA[
ValidationResult isValid(Object o, TransformerContext ctx);
    ]]></source>
    This method signature basically means that a <code>Validator</code> is passed
    an object and has to decide whether this object is valid or not.
    (We will explain the helper classes <code>ValidationResult</code> and
    <code>TransformerContext</code> in a moment.)
  </p>
  <p>
    A <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/Transformer.html">Transformer</a></code>
    deals with data conversions from one data type into another one. Focusing on
    use cases related to forms such conversions are necessary twice in the
    life-cycle of a typical form:
    <ul>
    <li>When the form is opened its input fields have to be initialized with data
    from the application's data model. This typically involves a transformation
    from model-specific data types (e.g. numbers, dates) to strings needed for
    GUI controls.</li>
    <li>When the user presses the OK button the data entered into the input
    fields has to be stored in the model. This implies the inverse transformation,
    i.e. from plain strings to model-specific data types. Of course, this
    transformation can only be successful if the data entered by the user adheres
    to the expected format. So usually a <code>Validator</code> is involved, too,
    which checks the validity of the data entered before the transformation is
    actually performed.</li>
    </ul>
    The <code>Transformer</code> interface also consists only of a single method
    that looks as follows:
    <source><![CDATA[
Object transform(Object o, TransformerContext ctx) throws Exception;
    ]]></source>
    This can be read as: an object comes in and another one (the result of the
    transformation applied by this <code>Transformer</code>) goes out.
  </p>
  <p>
    In both method signatures an argument of type
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/TransformerContext.html">
    TransformerContext</a></code> appeared. An object implementing this interface
    provides useful information for the <code>Transformer</code> or
    <code>Validator</code> that may be needed for performing the transformation
    or validation. The major part of the <code>TransformerContext</code>
    interface is related to internationalization, which is an important aspect
    of the tasks to be performed by <code>Transformer</code> and
    <code>Validator</code> implementations. For instance, different countries
    use different formats for dates or numbers, so transformers dealing with
    such data types have to be aware of the current locale.
    The <code>TransformerContext</code> interface can be used for obtaining the
    following information:
    <ul>
    <li>The current <code>Locale</code>.</li>
    <li>The current <em>resource manager</em>. This may be useful if
    lanugage-specific texts need to be generated.</li>
    <li>A <code>ValidationMessageHandler</code> object (this is discussed later).
    </li>
    <li>A map with properties that can be used to alter the behavior of
    <code>Transformer</code> or <code>Validator</code> implementations.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>isValid()</code> method of the <code>Validator</code> interface
    returns an object implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ValidationResult.html">
    ValidationResult</a></code>. Through this interface the status of the
    validation can be obtained. There are two methods:
    <ul>
    <li><code>isValid()</code> returns a boolean flag that determines whether
    the validation was successful. If <code>isValid()</code> returns <b>true</b>,
    the user has entered valid data.</li>
    <li><code>getErrorMessages()</code> returns one or more error messages
    related to the validation. Error messages are only available if
    <code>isValid()</code> returns <b>false</b>. In this case it is important to
    tell the user what exactly was wrong. This information is contained in the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ValidationMessage.html">
    ValidationMessage</a></code> objects returned by <code>getErrorMessages()</code>.
    A <code>ValidationMessage</code> consists of a key and a text to be displayed
    to the user. More details about <code>ValidationMessage</code> and how
    instances can be created will be discussed later.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Existing classes">
  <p>
    The library ships with a number of default transformers and validators that
    support the most primitive data types (including date and time) and can be
    used out of the box. These implementations are pretty powerful and provide
    enhanced validation capabilities, e.g. comparing an input object with a
    reference value. The basic pattern is that there are abstract base classes
    like <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/DateTransformerBase.html">
    DateTransformerBase</a></code> or
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/NumberTransformerBase.html">
    NumberTransformerBase</a></code> that implement both the <code>Transformer</code>
    and the <code>Validator</code> interface in a generic way. They provide the
    major part of the functionality required. Then there are a bunch of
    concrete classes derived from these base classes that are specialized for
    concrete data types (e.g. Date, Integer, Long, Float, ...). The Javadocs of
    these classes list the various configuration options of these classes and
    also the validation error messages they can produce.
  </p>
  <p>
    In addition to the implementations dealing with specific data types there
    are some more fully functional classes that can be used for special
    purposes:
    <ul>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ToStringTransformer.html">
    ToStringTransformer</a></code> implements a generic way for transforming
    objects to a text representation. Some special types of objects are directly
    recognized and formatted accordingly to the current locale, e.g. date types
    and numbers. On unknown objects the <code>toString()</code> method is
    invoked.</li>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/RequiredValidator.html">
    RequiredValidator</a></code> is a fully functional <code>Validator</code>
    implementation that can be assigned to input fields that are mandatory. It
    can deal with different types of objects like strings, collections, or arrays.
    and can check whether they are empty. In this case validation fails. A value
    of <b>null</b> is of course always considered invalid.</li>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/RegexValidator.html">
    RegexValidator</a></code> uses a regular expression to validate user input.
    An instance can be initialized with a regular expression string that must be
    compatible with the regular expression syntax defined for the
    <code>java.util.regex.Pattern</code> class. The user input to be validated
    is transformed to a string and matched against the defined pattern. If this
    is not possible, a validation error is produced. This is a very powerful
    means to enforce certain input patterns.</li>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ChainValidator.html">
    ChainValidator</a></code> allows combining multiple validators so that an
    input value is considered valid only if all of these child validators return
    a positive result. This is useful if multiple conditions have to be checked
    that are implemented by different <code>Validator</code> implementations. A
    good use case are required input fields of a specific data type: The
    existing validators for primitive types (e.g. dates or numbers) all accept
    <b>null</b> input. In order to declare mandatory input fields these validators
    can be combined with a <code>RequiredValidator</code> using
    <code>ChainValidator</code>.
    </li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Creating a custom transformer">
  <p>
    Implementing a custom <code>Transformer</code> is a pretty straight forward
    task. A <code>Transformer</code> class requires the <code>transform()</code>
    method. Here a custom implementation is free to do whatever it wants. It
    can even throw an arbitrary exception if the transformation fails for some
    reason. The <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/TransformerContext.html">
    TransformerContext</a></code> object being passed to the
    <code>transform()</code> method can be queried for specific properties set
    in the context or for information about the current locale.
  </p>
  <p>
    Transformers are typically specific for a given data type. So there are no
    general rules that can be stated here. However, one important point is that
    a transformer is typically combined with a validator: the validator first
    checks the input of the user, and if this validations succeeds, the
    transformation should be possible without throwing an exception. Because of
    this narrow relationship between validation and transformation many of the
    functional classes in the <code>transform</code> package implement both the
    <code>Transformer</code> and the <code>Validator</code> interfaces.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Creating a custom validator">
  <p>
    Implementing a custom <code>Validator</code> is usually more involved than a
    new <code>Transformer</code> implementation because the validator has to
    provide concrete information to the user if something goes wrong. This
    includes the definition of meaningful error messages that are returned as
    part of the <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ValidationResult.html">
    ValidationResult</a></code> object returned by the validator. As an example
    we are going to develop a validator that checks whether a password entered
    by the user is strong enough. The password must have at least a configurable
    number of characters and include characters from all the three groups
    letters, digits, and special characters.
  </p>
  <p>
    We can start by thinking about the possible error messages our new validator
    can produce. There are two error conditions: the password may be too short,
    and it may be too simple (i.e. it does not contain characters from all three
    character groups defined above). To define the exact error texts we define
    a new resource group, say <em>validationerrors</em>. (The framework has
    already a resource group <em>validators</em>, which contains the error
    messages of the default <code>Validator</code> classes.) So we create a
    file <code>validationerrors.properties</code> with the following content:
    <source><![CDATA[
ERR_PWD_TOOSHORT = The passowrd must have at least {0} characters.
ERR_PWD_TOOSIMPLE = The password must contain letters, digits, and special characters.
    ]]></source>
  </p>
  <p>
    Important are the keys used for the resource texts. They are later used by
    the implementation class to refer to the error messages. Notice that the
    first error message contains a place holder for the number of characters a
    password must have; this value can be configured, so we cannot specify a fix
    number.
  </p>
  <p>
    Error messages are obtained from an object implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ValidationMessageHandler.html">
    ValidationMessageHandler</a></code> interface that lives in the
    <code>TransformerContext</code>. The default implementation of this
    interface is provided by the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/DefaultValidationMessageHandler.html">
    DefaultValidationMessageHandler</a></code> class.
    The <code>ValidationMessageHandler</code> interface defines a
    <code>getValidationMessage()</code> method, which is passed the key of an
    error message and returns a <code>ValidationMessage</code> object with the
    corresponding message. <code>DefaultValidationMessageHandler</code>
    implements this method by first checking whether an object with the passed
    in key can be found in the properties of the current
    <code>TransformerContext</code>. If this is the case, this object is used
    as error message. Otherwise, the key is interpreted as a resource identifier,
    and a resource lookup is performed. Per default the class searches in the
    reserved <code>validators</code> resource group. But it can be configured
    to look in other resource groups, too. To do this we have to add a bean
    declaration like the following one in a bean definition file of our
    application:
    <source><![CDATA[
<di:bean name="jguiraffe.validationMessageHandler"
  beanClass="net.sf.jguiraffe.transform.DefaultValidationMessageHandler">
  <di:setProperty property="alternativeResourceGroups"
    value="validationerrors"/>
</di:bean>
    ]]></source>
    This bean declaration overrides the default declaration for the
    <code>validationMessageHandler</code> bean. In the new declaration we set
    the <em>alternativeResourceGroups</em> property. Here a comma-separated
    list of resource group names can be specified that are searched for error
    texts. This basically means that <code>DefaultValidationMessageHandler</code>
    searches for an error key in these resource groups first. If search is
    successful, the found resource text is used as error message. Otherwise it
    looks up the key in the default resource group.
  </p>
  <p>
    With the error messages in place we can start with the actual coding of the
    new <code>PasswordValidator</code> class. The <code>isValid()</code>
    method of this class has to check the length of the user input and whether
    the password is sufficiently complex. If this is true, a
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/ValidationResult.html">
    ValidationResultr</a></code> object indicating a successful validation has
    to be returned. Otherwise a result object has to be created with the
    appropriate error messages:
    <source><![CDATA[
public class PasswordValidator implements Validator
{
    /** Error key for a password that is too short. */
    public static final String ERR_PWD_TOOSHORT = "ERR_PWD_TOOSHORT";

    /** Error key for a password that is too simple. */
    public static final String ERR_PWD_TOOSIMPLE = "ERR_PWD_TOOSIMPLE";

    /** Constant for the default minimum length of a password. */
    private static final int DEFAULT_MIN_LENGTH = 6;

    /** The minimum number of characters for a valid password. */
    private int minimumLength = DEFAULT_MIN_LENGTH;

    /**
     * Returns the minimum length a password must have.
     * @return the minimum length of a valid password
     */
    public int getMinimumLength()
    {
        return minimumLength;
    }

    /**
     * Sets the minimum length a password must have.
     * @param len the minimum length of a valid password
     */
    public void setMinimumLength(int len)
    {
        minimumLength = len;
    }

    /**
     * Performs the validation.
     */
    public ValidationResult isValid(Object o, TransformerContext ctx)
    {
        String pwd = (o == null) ? "" : String.valueOf(o);

        // long enough?
        boolean tooShort = pwd.length() < getMinimumLength();

        // complexity?
        int letters = 0;
        int digits = 0;
        int special = 0;
        for (int i = 0; i < pwd.length(); i++)
        {
            char c = pwd.charAt(i);

            if ((c >= 'a' && c <= 'z') || (c >= 'A' && c <= 'Z'))
            {
                letters++;
            }
            else if (c >= '0' && c <= '9')
            {
                digits++;
            }
            else
            {
                special++;
            }
        }
        boolean tooSimple = letters < 1 || digits < 1 || special < 1;

        // Everything okay?
        if (!tooShort && !tooSimple)
        {
            return DefaultValidationResult.VALID;
        }

        // Otherwise create correct error messages
        ValidationMessageHandler msgHandler = ctx.getValidationMessageHandler();
        DefaultValidationResult.Builder builder =
            new DefaultValidationResult.Builder();

        if (tooShort)
        {
            builder.addErrorMessage(msgHandler.getValidationMessage(ctx,
                ERR_PWD_TOOSHORT, getMinimumLength()));
        }
        if (tooSimple)
        {
            builder.addErrorMessage(msgHandler.getValidationMessage(ctx,
                ERR_PWD_TOOSIMPLE));
        }

        return builder.build();
    }
}
    ]]></source>
  </p>
  <p>
    At the beginning of the class we declare some constants for the possible
    error messages. The values of these constants must match the keys we used
    for the resources of the error texts. The minimum length of valid passwords
    should be configurable, so we created a property with get and set methods
    for it.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>isValid()</code> method contains the actual logic. First we
    convert the object passed in to a string (because it can be <b>null</b> a
    corresponding check is required). Then we implement our checks. If they
    succeed, the <code>VALID</code> constant of the class
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/transform/DefaultValidationResult.html">
    DefaultValidationResultr</a></code> is returned, which represents a valid
    result.
  </p>
  <p>
    The remaining part of the code deals with the construction of a
    <code>ValidationResult</code> object that contains the appropriate error
    messages. In order to obtain the error messages we need a
    <code>ValidationMessageHandler</code> object, which can be queried from the
    <code>TransformerContext</code>. Objects of the class
    <code>DefaultValidationResult</code> cannot be created directly, rather the
    class defines a nested <code>Builder</code> class (an application of the
    <em>builder</em> pattern). Such a <code>Builder</code> object is created,
    then the error messages for the failed checks are added to it. Notice that
    for the error <code>ERR_PWD_TOOSHORT</code> the required minimum length is
    passed as parameter to the <code>getValidationMessage()</code> method. It
    will become part of the error message to be displayed to the user.
  </p>
  <p>
    This concludes our excourse in writing custom validators. The validator and
    transformer classes shipped with the library are also good examples for
    more or less complex validation tasks; so having a look at them may be
    useful.
  </p>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>