<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2017 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: formcontroller.xml 205 2012-01-29 18:29:57Z oheger $ -->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Form controllers</title>
  <author email="oheger@users.sourceforge.net">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Form controllers">
  <p>
    In the section about <a href="forms.html">forms</a> we have already seen how
    the <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/Form.html">Form</a></code>
    class provides support for many tasks related to the handling of forms like
    reading and writing the contents of input elements or performing validation.
    Compared with the amount of code that would be required if all these steps
    were implemented by hand this is certainly a major improvement. However, it
    is still not the full story
  </p>
  <p>
    While the <code>Form</code> class implements a great deal of functionality
    needed for the handling of a form's data it leaves some important questions
    unanswered:
    <ul>
      <li>When should initial values be written into the input fields of the
      form?</li>
      <li>When should validation be performed?</li>
      <li>How are validation results presented to the user?</li>
      <li>When should the form be closed and what should be done with the data
      entered by the user?</li>
      <li>The user must also be able to cancel the form and throw away all the
      data entered so far.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    These issues are closely related to the <em>life cycle</em> of a form. In
    desktop applications a form is always associated with a (dialog) window.
    When the window pops up the input fields must be initialized. While the user
    interacts with the input elements validation can be performed and fields
    containing invalid data can be highlighted somehow. Typically the window
    contains buttons which can be used to commit or to cancel the form. If the
    user presses the <em>OK</em> button, the data entered has to be validated
    again and - if validation succeeds - stored in the model for further
    processing. Then the window can be closed. The <em>Cancel</em> button in
    contrast directly closes the window.
  </p>
  <p>
    In the <em>JGUIraffe</em> library a <em>form controller</em> is responsible
    for managing the life-cycle of a form. It establishes the connection
    between the <code>Form</code> class and the data it maintains and the
    window that embeds the form.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Fundamental concepts">
  <p>
    It is an unwritten law that all libraries that deal with the processing of
    user input must emphasize that they implement the <em>model view controller
    (MVC) pattern</em> in some way. This is a design pattern which has proven to
    be successful especially in UI development. It focuses on the separation
    between the graphical component that presents data to the user (the view)
    and the component that stores the data (the model). A third component,
    the controller, evaluates user actions in the view and updates the model
    correspondingly. So the controller mediates between the model and the view.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <em>JGUIraffe</em> library is no exception from this rule. It also
    adheres to the separation between model, view, and controller by making use
    of the following components:
    <ul>
    <li>The model can be an arbitrary data object appropriate for the
    application. It must be capable of storing all data a user can enter in
    the form's input fields.</li>
    <li>The view is the dialog window displayed to the user containing all
    input elements of the form.</li>
    <li>The controller is represented by an object of the class
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormController.html">
    FormController</a></code> or a derived class. Together with an instance of
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/Form.html">Form</a></code>
    the interaction between the model and the view is managed.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    In this section we focus on the <code>FormController</code> class. The idea
    is that every time a window displaying a form is constructed, an instance of
    <code>FormController</code> is created, too, and associated with both the
    window and the <code>Form</code> object managing the user's input. After its
    creation the <code>FormController</code> object is registered as listener
    for various events at the window and its input components. Thus it receives
    notifications for important status changes and can react accordingly, e.g.
    by invoking methods on the <code>Form</code> object.
  </p>
  <p>
    For instance, when the window is opened for the first time the controller
    object reveives a corresponding event. It can then trigger the
    <code>Form</code> object to fetch initial values from its model and to write
    it into the input components.
  </p>
  <p>
    The form controller is also aware of the actions that can close the form -
    namely the buttons for <em>Okay</em> and <em>Cancel</em>. If corresponding
    events are received, it can trigger a validation and decide whether the
    window can be closed. It is also possible to configure
    <a href="commands.html">command objects</a> that are to be executed when
    the form is closed on reaction of an <em>Okay</em> or <em>Cancel</em>
    action. This allows an application to immediately process the data entered
    by the user.
  </p>
  <p>
    Finally, a <code>FormController</code> object can act itself as an event
    source. It can send certain events releated to changes in the validation
    status of input fields. Such events are fired for instance after each
    validation operation. Interested components can register as listeners for
    these events and perform corresponding UI updates. For instance, if a
    validation operation detects that a field contains invalid data, an event
    listener can highlight this input field.
  </p>
  <p>
    This was a high-level overview over the functionality provided by the
    <code>FormController</code> class. We will now discuss its API in more
    detail.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="The FormController API">
  <p>
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormController.html">
    FormController</a></code> is a concrete class and can be used as is. If a
    dialog window has specific requirements that go beyond the standard
    functionality for input validation and processing provided by the class, a
    custom class can be created that extends <code>FormController</code>.
  </p>
  <p>
    After the creation of an instance some references to dependent objects must
    be set. This way the controller is associated with the <code>Form</code>
    object and other components it has to interact with. Typically a developer
    does not have to care about the initialization of a form controller; the
    framework performs all necessary steps behind the scenes (we will discuss
    this in more detail when we describe the <em>builders</em> provided by
    <em>JGUIraffe</em>). In this subsection we assume that a
    <code>FormController</code> instance has already been created and
    initialized and focus on the methods that can be used to customize this
    instance.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>FormController</code> object must be able to detect when the user
    wants to close the dialog window. Depending on the action triggered by the
    user (OK or Cancel) the controller has to react accordingly to ensure that
    the data entered by the user is processed correctly. In order to detect
    clicks on the OK or the Cancel button the controller has to know the names
    of the corresponding button components. For this purpose the methods
    <code>setBtnOkName()</code> and <code>setBtnCancelName()</code> are used.
    Both methods expect a string with the name of the corresponding button. The
    controller registeres itself as action listener at these button components
    so that it is notified when the user clicks on these buttons.
  </p>
  <p>
    Further properties and methods of the <code>FormController</code> class are
    related to the handling of validation operations. First there is the
    <code>validate()</code> method which performs a validation of the form
    associated with the controller and returns the results. The method can be
    called at any time; the controller also calls it at certain points in the
    life-cycle of the dialog window, e.g. after it is opened or when the user
    clicks the OK button. A validation also causes all registered listeners of
    type <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormControllerValidationListener.html">
    FormControllerValidationListener</a></code> to be notified. Listeners of
    this type can be added using the <code>addValidationListener()</code>
    method.
  </p>
  <p>
    The default behavior of the <code>FormController</code> class when the user
    presses the OK button is to perform a validation to ensure that all data
    entered so far is valid. If this is not the case, a message box with
    validation messages is displayed, and the form cannot be closed. There are a
    couple of methods to configure the message box displayed in this situation:
    <ul>
    <li><code>setMessageOutput()</code> allows setting the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/utils/MessageOutput.html">
    MessageOutput</a></code> object that is used for displaying the message box.
    If no specific <code>MessageOutput</code> object is set, the
    application-global default object is used - which is probably desired in
    most cases. One use case for this method is to suppress the message box with
    validation errors at all. This can be done by setting a
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/utils/NullMessageOutput.html">
    NullMessageOutput</a></code> object.</li>
    <li>With the <code>setValidationMessageBoxCaption()</code> method the title
    of the message box with validation messages can be determined. If no title
    has been set, a default title (defined by a default resource ID and obtained
    through the current resource manager) is used.</li>
    <li>Finally it is possible to influence the content of the message box with
    validation messages. This can be achieved by passing a
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/FormValidationMessageFormat.html">
    FormValidationMessageFormat</a></code> object to the
    <code>setValidationMessageFormat()</code> method.
    <code>FormValidationMessageFormat</code> can translate a list of validation
    messages to a plain string which can then be displayed in a message box.
    Again, a default object is used if no custom format object is specified.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Processing of form data">
  <p>
    When the user clicks the OK or the Cancel button (or performs a corresponding
    action, e.g. pressing the Escape key) the dialog window has to be
    closed. In addition, the controller can be instructed to execute specific
    code which reacts on the closing of the form. This is a convenient way to
    immediately process the data entered by the user. For instance, if the
    current form allows entering the data for a new domain object, code can
    be invoked in reaction of the OK button which writes the data into the
    database.
  </p>
  <p>
    There are two ways to execute code when the dialog window associated with
    the controller is closed:
    <ul>
      <li>It is possible to set <em>command objects</em> that are to be executed
      for the OK and the Cancel action using the methods
      <code>setOkCommand()</code> and <code>setCancelCommand()</code>
      respective. When the associated dialog window is closed the controller
      checks whether a command is defined for the corresponding closing type
      (OK or Cancel). If this is the case, the command is put into the global
      command queue and executed by a worker thread - hence the UI does not
      block. (Refer to the <a href="commands.html">Commands</a> section for
      more information about commands and their execution.) By making use of
      command objects complex operations can be performed with the data entered
      in the form, e.g. database or file operations.</li>
      <li>Another option is to register special event listeners at the
      controller. The <code>addFormListener()</code> method expects an object
      implementing the
      <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormControllerFormListener.html">
      FormControllerFormListener</a></code> interface. This interface
      defines a single <code>formClosed()</code> method which is called when the
      dialog window associated with the controller is closed. It is passed a
      <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormControllerFormEvent.html">
      FormControllerFormEvent</a></code> object which contains information about
      the way the form was closed. So the listener can react accordingly. The
      main difference between the event listener approach and command objects is
      that event listeners are directly called from within the event dispatch
      thread. Therefore they are appropriate for short-running operations only.
      If processing of form data takes a little longer, a command object should
      be preferred; otherwise the UI might become non-responsive.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The two options for processing form data when the form was closed are not
    mutual exclusive. It is well possible to define both a command and an event
    listener. This may make sense in certain situations, e.g. the event listener
    could update the UI to give the user some feedback while a command performs
    a longer-running operation in the background.
  </p>
  <p>
    The use of command objects or event listeners for the processing of form data is
    one reason why the <code>FormController</code> class can be used out of the
    box: There is no need to override methods that define how the data is to be
    processed; just associate the controller with corresponding command objects
    or listeners. Note that these associations are fully optional. If there are
    no commands nor event listeners, the dialog window is just closed without
    performing any further steps - of course, if the OK button is pressed, the
    data entered by the user is copied into the model object of the form.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Additional validation support">
  <p>
    One important task of a <code>FormController</code> instance is to provide
    feedback about the current validation status of the form's input fields. In
    most cases the user wants to see directly if fields contain invalid data.
    However, there is no default strategy that defines how and when such a
    feedback is to be provided. An application may decide to do without
    immediate validation feedback. In this scenario a validation is performed
    only at the end of data entering, i.e. when the user hits the OK button.
    Other applications might want to provide a feedback earlier, e.g. after the
    user leaves an input field or even as soon as data is typed in. All of these
    strategies have their specific advantages and disadvantages, and a library
    supporting forms should be flexible enough to support all of them.
  </p>
  <p>
    The next question is the way how feedback about invalid fields is to be
    given. Again there are multiple possibilities thinkable, for instance
    <ul>
    <li>input fields containing invalid data are somehow highlighted, e.g. they
    could be given different colors or a warning icon could be displayed next
    to them.</li>
    <li>tool tipps for input fields can be adapted dynamically to show hints
    if the fields have invalid content.</li>
    <li>there can be a specialized area in the form window that displays the
    current validation messages.</li>
    </ul>
    So this is another area where a large amount of flexibility is required.
  </p>
  <p>
    Let's tackle the question about when to perform validation first: A form
    controller can be passed an object implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormValidationTrigger.html">
    FormValidationTrigger</a></code> interface to its
    <code>setValidationTrigger()</code> method. This object decides when a
    validation is to be performed. The <code>FormValidationTrigger</code>
    interface is surprisingly simple: it defines only the single method
    <code>initTrigger()</code> that is passed a reference to the current
    <code>FormController</code>. The background behind this concept is that a
    <code>FormValidationTrigger</code> object is not queried by the controller,
    but it becomes active itself when it decides that a validation is required
    now. A typical implementation will use the <code>FormController</code>
    reference passed to its <code>initTrigger()</code> method to register itself
    as event listener for all necessary events. In the event handler methods it
    can then call back to the controller and initiate a validation operation.
    <em>JGUIraffe</em> ships with the following concrete implementations of the
    <code>FormValidationTrigger</code> interface:
    <ul>
      <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormValidationTriggerNone.html">
      FormValidationTriggerNone</a></code> never triggers a validation. This is
      appropriate if no immediate feedback about invalid data is to be provided.
      If this trigger is used, a validation is only performed when the user
      presses the OK button (this validation is independent from a validation
      trigger).</li>
      <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormValidationTriggerFocus.html">
      FormValidationTriggerFocus</a></code> registers itself as form-global
      focus listener. Thus it is notified whenever the user leaves an input
      field. Then it triggers a validation operation. This seems to be a good
      compromise: the user is not disturbed by changing validation hints while
      typing, but the messages are pretty up-to-date.
      <code>FormValidationTriggerFocus</code> is the default trigger used when
      no specific trigger was set.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code>FormValidationTrigger</code> interface determines when a validation
    of the user input is to be performed. It does not answer the question what
    to do when invalid input fields are detected. Because there is a wide range
    of possible options to handle invalid input fields there is no specific
    interface for this purpose. Rather, the <code>FormController</code> class
    provides a generic event listener mechanism that allows interested components
    to be notified when certain events related to the validation status of
    input fields occur. The following event listener interfaces are supported:
    <ul>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormControllerValidationListener.html">
    FormControllerValidationListener</a></code> objects are added using the
    <code>addValidationListener()</code> method. They are notified whenever the
    controller's <code>validate()</code> method is invoked. The event object
    passed to these listeners also contains an object with the results of the
    validation.</li>
    <li><code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/FormControllerFieldStatusListener.html">
    FormControllerFieldStatusListener</a></code> objects are added using the
    <code>addFieldStatusListener()</code> method. They are notified when the
    <em>visited</em> status of an input field changes, i.e. when the user leaves
    an input field for the first time. The background is that fields containing
    invalid data may be treated differently depending on their visited status.
    Consider a form that declares some fields as mandatory. When the form is
    opened these fields are not yet filled in and thus are invalid. An application
    may not want to present the user a full list with error messages at the
    very beginning of data entering. Only if the user enters and leaves a field
    its validity should be taken into account. With listeners for the field
    status this use case can be implemented. (Note: When the user hits the OK
    button all input fields are marked as visited.)</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    These event listener interfaces allow interested components to keep track of
    the validation status of all input fields in the form. The <em>JGUIraffe</em>
    library provides a couple of classes implementing these interfaces that can
    be used out of the box to present hints related to validation results to the
    user.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/ColorFieldMarker.html">
    ColorFieldMarker</a></code> class tracks the validation status of input
    fields and changes their foreground and background colors correspondingly.
    A <code>ColorFieldMarker</code> can be configured with specific foreground
    and background colors for the possible validation states (e.g. colors for
    fields that are invalid, for which validation warnings exist, which are
    invalid, but have not yet been visited and so on). When an event from the
    <code>FormController</code> is received the <code>ColorFieldMarker</code>
    object determines all input fields whose validation status has changed. It
    then obtains the colors corresponding to the current status of each field
    and sets them. If for a specific validation status no colors are defined,
    the original colors of this input field are set (with other words: the color
    of such fields is not changed). The following image shows a simple dialog
    window with input fields that have been marked according to their validation
    status:
  </p>
  <img src="../images/userguide/ColorFieldMarker.png"
    alt="Dialog with input fields marked by ColorFieldMarker"/>
  <p>
    In this example the <em>File name</em> input field is invalid because the
    file name contains characters which are not allowed. For invalid fields that
    have already been visited the background color is set to red. The yellow
    background color of the <em>File content</em> input field indicates a
    validation warning. The warning was issued because the field is empty. The
    background color of this field is only changed if it has already been
    visited. So when the dialog window opens the field is displayed with its
    normal background color (white) even if it is empty.
  </p>
  <p>
    Another specialized <code>FormControllerValidationListener</code>
    implementation is
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/window/ctrl/ToolTipFieldMarker.html">
    ToolTipFieldMarker</a></code>. As the name implies,
    <code>ToolTipFieldMarker</code> uses the tool tips of input elements to
    provide information about validation errors or warnings to the user.
    Whenever a validation event is received the <code>ToolTipFieldMarker</code>
    object checks whether fields with validation errors or warnings exist. If
    this is the case, the messages are extracted and added to the tool tips of
    the corresponding elements. The user only has to move the mouse cursor over
    an input field to see the messages available for this field.
    <code>ToolTipFieldMarker</code> can be used together with
    <code>ColorFieldMarker</code>. In this case the colors of input fields
    indicate whether they contain valid data or not. The actual validation
    messages can then be displayed by simply moving the mouse cursor over the
    field.
  </p>
  <p>
    A <code>ToolTipFieldMarker</code> object is associated with an instance of
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/FormValidationMessageFormat.html">
    FormValidationMessageFormat</a></code>. This object determines how the
    validation messages are transformed to plain text which is then displayed
    in the tool tips. Please refer to the documentation of
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/FormValidationMessageFormat.html">
    FormValidationMessageFormat</a></code> for the possible options to customize
    this transformation.
  </p>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>