<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2021 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: osgi.xml 212 2012-07-14 15:22:35Z oheger $ -->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>OSGi</title>
  <author email="oheger@apache.org">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
  <section name="JGUIraffe and OSGi">
  <p>
    OSGi is a framework focusing on modularity of Java applications. It becomes
    more and more popular, so you may want to run your <em>JGUIraffe</em>
    application in an OSGi container. This is possible, but there are some
    aspects to be aware of. In this chapter these topics are discussed.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Bundles">
  <p>
    In order to deploy an application into an OSGi framework, it has to be
    packaged in so-called <em>bundles</em> - jar archives containing special
    meta data. From version 1.2 on, the <em>JGUIraffe</em> jar is a valid OSGi
    bundle. This is also true for the integration jars for the supported target
    platforms. They all contain the necessary meta data and thus can be directly
    deployed into your OSGi container of choice - you have to deploy the main
    jar plus the correct integration jar for the selected target platform.
  </p>
  <p>
    The <em>JGUIraffe</em> modules have some dependencies to other libraries
    (details can be found on the <a href="../dependencies.html">Dependencies</a>
    page). For a successful deployment into an OSGi container, all these
    dependencies have to be available as well. Unfortunately, not all of them
    support OSGi out of the box.
  </p>
  <p>
    Newer releases of the <a href="http://commons.apache.org">Apache Commons</a> components
    referenced by <em>JGUIraffe</em> already contain OSGi meta data, but some of
    the older releases do not. Especially the Commons Jelly jar is (at the time of this writing) not provided
    as an OSGi bundle. Because these dependencies have to be satisfied when
    installing the <em>JGUIraffe</em> bundle in an OSGi framework you have to
    obtain OSGi-enabled versions of the affected libraries. One option could be
    to re-package the jars as OSGi bundles yourself. Using the
    <a href="http://felix.apache.org/site/apache-felix-maven-bundle-plugin-bnd.html">
    Apache felix maven bundle plug-in</a> this is not too complicated. For
    instance,
    <a href="http://www.sonatype.com/index.php/Support/Books/The-Maven-Cookbook">
    The Maven Cookbook</a> contains a chapter about OSGi development which
    also covers the creation of OSGi bundles for existing jars.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Class loading">
  <p>
    A major feature of OSGi is that it enforces a very strict class loading
    architecture allowing each bundle only access to classes it explicitly
    references in its OSGi meta data. Especially for the dependency injection
    framework of <em>JGUIraffe</em> this has a big impact because classes have
    to be used which are defined in client bundles unknown to <em>JGUIraffe</em>.
  </p>
  <p>
    The dependency injection framework uses an object implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/ClassLoaderProvider.html">
    ClassLoaderProvider</a></code> interface to resolve classes. When starting
    up, the central
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
    Application</a></code> object creates and initializes such a
    <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> object. Per default, it sets the class
    loader which loaded the custom application class as default class loader.
    For many simple applications this is exactly what you want because this is
    typically the class loader of the client bundle. So referenced classes can
    directly be obtained from this bundle. If you have a more complicated
    setup, you should override the <code>initClassLoaderProvider()</code>
    method of your <code>Application</code> class to register all involved
    class loaders with specific names. In your builder scripts you have to
    make sure that the correct class loaders are referenced.
  </p>
  <p>
    There is one caveat: To ensure that the current
    <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> is actually used in a builder script,
    always specify class references using tag attributes ending on
    <code>ClassName</code>. Do not use the simpler attributes with the
    <code>Class</code> suffix. For instance, the following fragment shows a
    <strong>wrong example</strong> of declaring a <code>FileSystemManager</code>
    bean from the Apache Commons VFS project (using a static factory method) in
    an OSGi environment:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
  <di:bean name="fileSystemManager"
    beanClass="org.apache.commons.vfs2.FileSystemManager">
    <di:factory>
      <di:methodInvocation method="getManager"
        targetClass="org.apache.commons.vfs2.VFS">
      </di:methodInvocation>
    </di:factory>
  </di:bean>
  ]]></source>
  <p>
    Note the usage of the <code>beanClass</code> and <code>targetClass</code>
    attributes. The <strong>correct</strong> bean declaration is as follows:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
  <di:bean name="fileSystemManager"
    beanClassName="org.apache.commons.vfs2.FileSystemManager">
    <di:factory>
      <di:methodInvocation method="getManager"
        targetClassName="org.apache.commons.vfs2.VFS">
      </di:methodInvocation>
    </di:factory>
  </di:bean>
  ]]></source>
  <p>
    Here the problematic attributes have been replaced by variants ending on
    <code>ClassName</code>. There are some more attributes falling into this
    category, e.g. <code>parameterClassName</code>. The reason why the
    attributes ending on <code>Class</code> cause problems in an OSGi container
    is that they are directly evaluated by the Jelly engine processing the
    builder script. This engine does not know about the
    <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> object and thus will probably use a wrong
    class loader. The <code>ClassName</code> attributes in contrast are
    processed by <em>JGUIraffe</em>; here different class loaders can be taken
    into account. Note that for each <code>ClassName</code> attribute there is
    a companion attribute ending on <code>Loader</code>. With this attribute a
    special class loader can be selected. In simple applications these
    attributes are typically not needed; if they are missing the default class
    loader is used. However, if an application deals with multiple OSGi
    bundles (and therefore multiple class loaders), it may be necessary to
    specify the correct class loader explicitly. In such a case the value of
    the <code>Loader</code> attribute must match the name of a class loader as
    it has been registered at the <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code>.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Startup and shutdown">
  <p>
    The OSGi environment also affects starting and shutdown of applications.
    Rather than providing a static <code>main()</code> method, application
    bundles are installed in an OSGi container and are started automatically by
    an OSGi-specific mechanism. One possibility is a <em>bundle activator</em>,
    i.e. a class implementing the <code>org.osgi.framework.BundleActivator</code>
    interface. The activator must be referenced from the bundle's manifest file.
  </p>
  <p>
    Stand-alone <em>JGUIraffe</em> applications typically define a class
    derived from
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
    Application</a></code> with a static <code>main()</code> method. The
    method creates an instance of this class and invokes the static
    <code>startup()</code> method inherited from <code>Application</code>. The
    bundle activator has to do the same in its <code>start()</code> method.
    Because starting up the application is an expensive operation - bean
    declarations have to be read, the UI is constructed, etc. - this should be
    done in a new thread, so that control can be passed back to the OSGi
    framework immediately. Also, an alternative
    <a href="application.html#Exit_handlers">exit handler</a> should be set to
    prevent that the Java virtual machine is just terminated. Rather, the
    OSGi framework should be shut down in a graceful way. This can be achieved
    by obtaining a reference to the system bundle using the reserved bundle ID
    0 and calling the <code>stop()</code> method on it.
  </p>
  <p>
    The following listing shows a full example of a bundle activator
    implementation. It can serve as a basis for own implementations. It assumes
    that there is a class called <code>Main</code> derived from
    <code>Application</code>; this is the application class to be started.
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
public class Activator implements BundleActivator
{
    /** The logger. */
    private final Log log = LogFactory.getLog(getClass());

    @Override
    public void start(BundleContext context) throws Exception
    {
        log.info("Starting application bundle.");
        final Runnable exitHandler = createExitHandler(context);
        new Thread()
        {
            @Override
            public void run()
            {
                Main main = new Main();
                main.setExitHandler(exitHandler);
                try
                {
                    Main.startup(main, new String[0]);
                }
                catch (ApplicationException e)
                {
                    log.error("Could not start application!", e);
                }
            }
        }.start();
    }

    @Override
    public void stop(BundleContext context) throws Exception
    {
        log.info("Stopping application bundle.");
    }

    /**
     * Creates the exit handler for the application. This handler will shutdown
     * the OSGi framework by stopping the system bundle.
     *
     * @param context the bundle context
     * @return the exit handler
     */
    private Runnable createExitHandler(final BundleContext context)
    {
        return new Runnable()
        {
            @Override
            public void run()
            {
                Bundle sysBundle = context.getBundle(0);
                try
                {
                    sysBundle.stop();
                }
                catch (BundleException bex)
                {
                    log.error("Could not stop OSGi framework!", bex);
                }
            }
        };
    }
  ]]></source>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>
