<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2022 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Standard dialogs</title>
 </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Standard dialogs">
  <p>
    Applications often need to display dialogs for specific tasks such as
    opening a file. UI libraries typically provide standard dialogs for these
    purposes. <em>JGUIraffe</em> offers an abstraction layer through which
    standard dialogs can be displayed and the data entered in them can be
    processed.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Usage pattern">
  <p>
    Concrete standard dialogs are made available via service interfaces located
    below the <code>net.sf.jguiraffe.gui.dlg</code> package. These interfaces
    usually define one or more <code>showXXX()</code> methods through which
    different variants of the underlying dialog can be displayed. The methods
    expect an object with dialog-specific options; this can be used to
    customize the dialog to a certain degree. There is a base class for all
    options classes in form of the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/AbstractDialogOptions.html">
    AbstractDialogOptions</a></code> class. It defines a number of
    properties that are common to all standard dialogs. A concrete dialog
    service defines its own option class or sometimes even multiple ones.
  </p>
  <p>
    When the user closes a standard dialog via the OK button a result is
    produced that needs to be passed back to the application. A dialog to open
    a file for example returns the <code>java.io.File</code> object that the
    user has selected. The propagation of the dialog result is done via a
    callback object that is defined in the options for the dialog. There is a
    generic result callback interface named
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/DialogResultCallback.html">
    DialogResultCallback</a></code>. The base class for all option classes,
    <code>AbstractDialogOptions</code>, expects such a callback object as a
    constructor argument; so this information must be provided when an instance
    is created. Optionally, an arbitrary context data object can be specified
    together with the callback. When the callback is invoked the data object is
    passed as well. Here an application can provide context information
    relevant for the processing of the dialog result.
  </p>
  <p>
    If the user cancels the dialog, per default no action is performed. (The
    result callback is not invoked because no result object is available.) It
    is, however, possible to specify a <em>canceled callback</em> (an object
    implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/DialogCanceledCallback.html">
    DialogCanceledCallback</a></code> interface). This is optional; if such a
    callback is present, it is invoked rather than the result callback when the
    dialog is canceled. (Again a context data object can be specified to be
    passed to the callback.)
  </p>
  <p>
    Instances of dialog services can be obtained via the dependency injection
    framework; they are declared in the standard beans definition file shipped
    with <em>JGUIraffe</em> and thus can be referenced from the application's
    bean context or from builder scripts. It is for instance possible to inject
    a service reference into a task or command object that is triggered by a
    UI element.
  </p>
  <p>
    In the following sub sections the usage of concrete dialog services is
    described. The examples provided with these discussions will further
    clarify the explanations made so far.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="FileChooserDialogService">
  <p>
    Allowing the user to select a file to be opened or saved is a frequent use
    case. UI platforms typically support this use case by providing their own
    dialog classes. Swing for instance has the <code>JFileChooser</code> class
    that contains a full implementation of a file selection dialog; in JavaFX
    there are the <code>FileChooser</code> and <code>DirectoryChooser</code>
    classes that delegate to standard dialogs of the operating system. The
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/FileChooserDialogService.html">
    FileChooserDialogService</a></code> service interface serves as an
    abstraction over these classes. It offers methods to support the following
    use cases:
    <ul>
      <li>Selecting a directory</li>
      <li>Selecting a single file to be opened</li>
      <li>Selecting multiple files to be opened</li>
      <li>Selecting a file to be saved</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    All service methods expect as single argument an options object that allows
    a customization of the resulting dialog. As the different types of dialogs
    supported by the service differ in the options that can be adjusted, there
    are multiple concrete option classes. All of them allow the configuration
    of standard dialog properties (the mandatory result callback, the optional
    canceled callback, and the optional dialog title). In addition, they define
    some properties specific to the dialog type.
  </p>
  <p>
    The dialog to choose a directory offers the fewest customization options.
    It is configured using an object of the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/DirectoryChooserOptions.html">
    DirectoryChooserOptions</a></code> class. It allows setting the initial
    directory that is to be displayed when the dialog is shown. The user can
    then confirm this directory or navigate to a different one.
  </p>
  <p>
    The dialogs for selecting files support some more configuration options.
    They are defined by the abstract base class
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/AbstractFileChooserOptions.html">
    AbstractFileChooserOptions</a></code>; from this class the two concrete
    option classes
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/FileChooserOptions.html">
    FileChooserOptions</a></code> and
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/MultiFileChooserOptions.html">
    MultiFileChooserOptions</a></code> are derived. (These classes only differ
    in the result type: the former expects a single <code>java.io.File</code>
    as result and is used for the dialogs to open a file and to save a file;
    the latter is used by the dialog to open multiple files and thus expects a
    list of files as result.) The configuration options defined by these
    classes include the following properties:
    <ul>
      <li>the initial directory to be displayed when the dialog is opened</li>
      <li>the initial file to be selected</li>
      <li>an arbitrary number of filters for file extensions; each filter
      consists of a description and a list of file extensions, e.g.
      <code>Images (*.jpg; *.gif; *.png)</code>; by selecting one of these
      filters, the user can restrict the files that are displayed in the
      dialog.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The example application defines an action that displays a dialog to open a
    file. The file is then opened with the application associated with its file
    extension. The code can be found in the <code>SelectAndOpenFileTask</code>
    class in the demo application. Here we present some fragments from this
    class.
  </p>
  <p>
    The open dialog should contain some filters for frequently used file types.
    For this purpose, the class defines a couple of constants of the type
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/dlg/filechooser/FileExtensionFilter.html">
    FileExtensionFilter</a></code>. Each filter corresponds to a specific file
    type and can consist of multiple file extensions:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
    /** Filter to display all files. */
    private static final FileExtensionFilter FILTER_ALL =
            new FileExtensionFilter(
                    TextResource.fromResourceID("fc_filter_all"),
                    FileExtensionFilter.EXT_ALL_FILES);

    /** Filter to display image files. */
    private static final FileExtensionFilter FILTER_IMAGES =
            new FileExtensionFilter(
                    TextResource.fromResourceID("fc_filter_images"), "jpg",
                    "jpeg", "gif", "bmp", "png");

    /** Filter to display audio files. */
    private static final FileExtensionFilter FILTER_AUDIO =
            new FileExtensionFilter(
                    TextResource.fromResourceID("fc_filter_audio"), "mp3",
                    "ogg", "wav", "au");

    /** Filter to display text files. */
    private static final FileExtensionFilter FILTER_TEXT =
            new FileExtensionFilter(
                    TextResource.fromResourceID("fc_filter_text"), "txt", "doc",
                    "pdf");

    /** The list of special file extension filters. */
    private static final List<FileExtensionFilter> FILTERS =
            Arrays.asList(FILTER_ALL, FILTER_IMAGES, FILTER_AUDIO, FILTER_TEXT);
    ]]></source>
  <p>
    Note that there is an explicit entry to list all files - the first one
    which is selected per default. In order to display the file chooser dialog,
    a reference to the dialog service must be available. It is passed to the
    constructor of the task class. We will see later how it is resolved in the
    builder script:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
    /** The service for displaying file chooser dialogs. */
    private final FileChooserDialogService fileChooserService;

    /**
     * Creates a new instance of {@code SelectAndOpenFileTask} and initializes
     * it with a reference to the file chooser service.
     *
     * @param service the file chooser service
     * @param ctrl the main window controller
     */
    public SelectAndOpenFileTask(FileChooserDialogService service,
            MainWndController ctrl)
    {
        fileChooserService = service;
        ...
    }
    ]]></source>
  <p>
    The service reference is used when the task gets executed, i.e. in its
    <code>run()</code> method. It is passed an options object with some
    configuration options. The options also contain the callback to be invoked
    with the file selected by the user:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
    @Override
    public void run()
    {
        DialogResultCallback<File, Void> callback =
                new DialogResultCallback<File, Void>()
                {
                    @Override
                    public void onDialogResult(File result, Void data)
                    {
                        openDialogResult(result);
                    }
                };
        FileChooserOptions options =
                new FileChooserOptions(callback)
                    .setTitleResource("fc_title")
                    .setFilters(FILTERS)
                    .setInitialDirectory(new File(System.getProperty("java.io.tmpdir")));
        fileChooserService.showOpenFileDialog(options);
    }

    /**
     * Opens the file that has been selected in the file chooser dialog.
     *
     * @param file the result file
     */
    private void openDialogResult(final File file)
    {
        ...
    }
    ]]></source>
  <p>
    The callback used by this example just delegates to a method that further
    processes the resulting <code>File</code> object; a context data object is
    not needed here, therefore, the callback is of type &lt;File, Void&gt;. As
    further configuration options a dialog title, a list of filters, and the
    initial directory are defined. (The latter is just set to the user's
    temporary folder. A more sophisticated implementation would probably store
    the directory of the last file that was selected; so the next time the
    dialog is opened, the user can continue in this same directory.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The one piece that is missing is the declaration of the
    <code>SelectAndOpenFileTask</code> instance in the builder script. (It is a
    task class that is associated with an action.) The bean definition is shown
    in the fragment below. The relevant part is the first parameter passed to
    the constructor. Here the file chooser service is referenced under its
    well-known name:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
  <!-- Extras select and open file task -->
  <di:bean name="selectAndOpenTask"
    beanClass="net.sf.jguiraffe.examples.tutorial.mainwnd.SelectAndOpenFileTask">
    <di:constructor>
      <di:param refName="jguiraffe.fileChooserService"/>
      <di:param refName="windowController"/>
    </di:constructor>
  </di:bean>
    ]]></source>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>