<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2025 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: index.xml 218 2012-11-15 20:56:00Z oheger $ -->
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="oheger@apache.org">Oliver Heger</author>
    <title>JGuiraffe</title>
  </properties>

<body>
  <section name="Welcome to JGUIraffe">
  <p>
    This is the official project site of the <em>JGUIraffe</em> library.
    <em>JGUIraffe</em> is a framework supporting the implementation of Java
    desktop applications using concepts like declarative UI definition,
    action and command objects, and dependency injection. On this page you find
    comprehensive documentation and download links. The documentation consists
    of the following parts:
    <ul>
      <li>
      The <em>JGUIraffe</em> reference documentation inlcuding a short
      <a href="introduction.html">introduction</a> or a
      <a href="userguide/user_guide.html">user's guide</a>. Aggregated
      <a href="apidocs/index.html">Javadocs</a> are available as well. Use the
      links on the left hand side menu to navigate to these documents. When
      learning the library this is the place to start.
      </li>
      <li>
      <a href="jguiraffe-parent/jguiraffe-examples/index.html">The JGUIraffe examples
      documentation</a> deals with the examples shipped with the library. This
      includes a description of the <em>JGUIraffe tutorial application</em> - an
      application which demonstrates many concepts of the library combined to a
      real world example.
      </li>
      <li>
      The <em>JGUIraffe</em> library consists of several sub modules. These can
      be accessed from the <em>Modules</em> menu. Here you find additional
      information specific to these modules like several types of development
      reports.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </p>

  <subsection name="News">
  <p>
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td>2022-11-05</td>
      <td>
        A new bugfix release 1.4.1 with some dependency updates triggered by
        dependabot.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2021-08-01</td>
      <td>
        After a long phase of inactivity, a new release has been published: 1.4.
        The release fixes again many problems with the JavaFX module, but also
        adds new features like support for system file chooser dialogs. In this
        release, also the minimum requirements for the JDK and Scala version
        have been updated: Java 1.8 is now required, the project can be built on
        a JDK 11. Scala 2.13 is now used for the JavaFX module.
      </td>
    </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2018-11-16</td>
    <td>
      The project has moved from SourceForge to GitHub.
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2016-07-17</td>
    <td>
      With release 1.3.1 a bugfix release of <em>JGUIraffe</em> is provided which
      mainly addresses problems in the JavaFX module. The new release can be
      obtained via the usual sources.
    </td>
  </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>2015-01-18</td>
      <td>
        Release 1.3 of <em>JGUIraffe</em>. In addition to Swing, <em>JGUIraffe</em>
        applications now support JavaFX as target platform. Downloads are available
        from the SourceForge project site; as usual, the artifacts can also be
        downloaded automatically from the Central Maven repository.
      </td>
    </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2012-11-15</td>
    <td>
    Release 1.2 of <em>JGUIraffe</em>. The library can now be used in an
    OSGi environment. The newest artifacts can be downloaded from
    <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/jguiraffe/">SourceForge</a>
    and are also available in the Central Maven repository.
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2012-02-12</td>
    <td>
    Release 1.1 of <em>JGUIraffe</em>. This is a maintenance release which
    contains some bug fixes and adds a couple of new features. Maven artifacts
    have been deployed to the Central Maven repository.
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2010-10-31</td>
    <td>
    The <em>JGUIraffe</em> jar has been deployed to the
    <a href="http://repo1.maven.org/maven2">Central Maven repository</a>.
    Projects using <a href="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven</a> as their build
    tool can now declare the <em>JGUIraffe</em> dependency as follows:
    <pre>
      <![CDATA[
    <dependency>
      <groupId>net.sf.jguiraffe</groupId>
      <artifactId>jguiraffe</artifactId>
      <version>1.0</version>
    </dependency>
      ]]>
    </pre>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2010-09-03</td>
    <td>
    Release 1.0 of <em>JGUIraffe</em>.
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>2010-08-26</td>
    <td>
    The <em>JGUIraffe</em> tutorial application is now available.
    </td>
  </tr>
  </table>
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Get it">
  <p>
    To use <em>JGUIraffe</em> in your projects, add the corresponding
    dependency to the build tool of your choice (they are available from
    <a href="http://repo1.maven.org/maven2">Maven Central</a>. Depending on the
    desired target platform, you can either use
  </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <dependency>
      <groupId>net.sf.jguiraffe</groupId>
      <artifactId>jguiraffe-swing</artifactId>
      <version>1.3.1</version>
    </dependency>
    ]]></source>
  <p>
    for Swing or
  </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
    <dependency>
      <groupId>net.sf.jguiraffe</groupId>
      <artifactId>jguiraffe-java-fx</artifactId>
      <version>1.3.1</version>
    </dependency>
    ]]></source>
  <p>
    for JavaFX. If you want to check out the code, follow the instructions
    under <a href="building.html">Maven build</a>.
  </p>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
