<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2015 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: overview.xml 205 2012-01-29 18:29:57Z oheger $ -->
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="oheger@users.sourceforge.net">Oliver Heger</author>
    <title>JGuiraffe Overview</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>
        In this section we provide an overview about this library. We will
        discuss some of the key concepts and show briefly how a developer can
        benefit from them.
      </p>

      <subsection name="The Main Application Object">
      <p>
        In each JGUIraffe application there is a single object, which represents
        the application as a whole. This object is also the main entry point in
        the application. It is an instance of the
        <code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
        Application</a></code> class or a class derived from it. (The base
        class usually works out of the box. If you have special requirements,
        e.g. for parameter processing or initialization, you can create a
        custom sub class of this class.)
      </p>
      <p>
        When your application starts this <code>Application</code> object
        performs a couple of initialization tasks. Among other things it
        <ul>
          <li>Reads in the application's configuration data.</li>
          <li>Initializes the whole framework based on the data obtained from
          the application's configuration.</li>
          <li>Sets up a <em>resource manager</em> for accessing data that
          depends on the user's locale.</li>
          <li>Creates the application's GUI. This step is discussed in more
          detail in the next section.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        When the application is up and running all interested components can
        easily obtain a reference to the central <code>Application</code>
        instance. This instance provides some important services like
        <ul>
          <li>Access to configuration data.</li>
          <li>Access to the application's resources, e.g. internationalized
          texts.</li>
          <li>A simple means for creating message boxes to be displayed to the
          user, e.g. for showing info screens or issuing error messages.</li>
          <li>The <code>Application</code> object holds a reference to an
          <em>application context</em>. This is an object, in which central data
          can be stored that is needed by multiple components.</li>
          <li>From the <code>Application</code> instance a factory object for
          creating the <em>GUI builder</em> can be obtained. The GUI builder
          allows the easy creation of GUI elements like windows and dialogs.
          More on that below.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        The typical way of starting a JGUIraffe application is to execute the
        <code>main()</code> method of the <code>Application</code> class.
        This will start the initialization phase, in which the configuration
        files are searched and processed and all necessary initialization steps
        are performed. If no problems occur, the application's main window is
        shown.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Defining the GUI">
      <p>
        For the definition of the application's graphical user interface
        JGUIraffe goes a special way: Windows, dialogs, and their content are
        defined in XML files. These files are interpreted using
        <a href="http://commons.apache.org/">Apache Commons</a>'s
        <a href="http://commons.apache.org/jelly/">Jelly</a>.
        They can contain elements that correspond to typical user
        interface controls like labels, text fields, and radio buttons. In
        addition all of the standard tags provided by Jelly and its tag
        libraries can be used. We refer to this approach as the <em>GUI
        builder</em>.
      </p>
      <p>
        Defining the user interface in separate configuration files instead of
        hard coding it in Java code has many advantages. It simplyfies a
        separation between GUI and business logic. Changing the GUI can be done
        without having to rebuild the code. With this approach even dynamically
        generated GUIs are possible.
      </p>
      <!-- TODO: Provide a simple example script here. -->
      <p>
        All tags for constructing GUI elements directly support
        internationalization. All texts to be displayed to the user can be
        defined as resource identifiers and are then resolved using the
        application's resource manager. Of course it is also possible to use
        text literals directly, but for applications that should present
        themselves in mutliple languages this is not recommended.
      </p>
      <p>
        It is important to notice that the XML tags do not directly create the
        corresponding GUI controls. Instead this task is delegated to a factory.
        It is thinkable to have different implementations of this factory. At
        the moment a factory implementation is provided that produces Swing
        controls. But another implementation that uses SWT/JFace would also be
        feasible. Because the JGUIraffe API hides the underlying GUI toolkit
        it would be possible to write programs that are indipendent on a concrete
        GUI toolkit; just by replacing the factory a different toolkit is used
        (well, in theory; this feature is a bit experimental).
      </p>
      <p>
        Scripts interpreted by the <em>GUI builder</em> are not limited to the
        definition of UI elements. In fact, JGUIraffe implements a lean, but
        fully functional <em>dependency injection framework</em>. This
        framework allows the definition of arbitrary Java objects in builder
        scripts with all their dependencies. This feature is especially useful
        for combining business logic with the user interface. For instance,
        controller objects can be defined and associated with UI elements like
        windows or input fields.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Layouts">
      <p>
        Complex layouts of GUI controls are always hard to deal with in Java
        applications. The fact that different GUI toolkits provide different
        layout managers does not simplify a developer's task either. For
        instance the layout managers used in SWT distinguish from the ones
        supported by Swing.
      </p>
      <p>
        Because JGUIraffe is intended to support a certain level of independence
        of a specific GUI toolkit a solution is needed to provide a set of
        powerful layout managers that can easily be ported to multiple target
        GUI toolkits. This is achieved through the family of the
        <em>Percent Layout Managers</em>.
      </p>
      <p>
        The basic idea behind these layout managers is to implement the layouting
        algorithm in a way independent on a concrete graphics library. To port
        such a layout to a specific GUI toolkit an adapter class must be
        provided, which deals with specifics like obtaining the preferred size
        of a control, setting its bounds, or implementing the appropriate
        layout manager interface. Again such an adapter exists for Swing so far,
        others should not be too complicated to implement.
      </p>
      <p>
        The fundamental layout class implemented in this library is the
        <code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/layout/PercentLayoutBase.html">
        PercentLayoutBase</a></code> class. <code>PercentLayoutBase</code> is
        especially useful for regular layouts, e.g. when multiple successive lines
        all have the same structure (for instance two or more columns
        consisting of a label and an input field). It devides the available
        space into a grid of rows and columns. For each row and column properties
        can be defined, which determine its size. So the size can be fixed or
        determined by the minimum or preferred width/height of the contained
        controls. In addition a weight factor can be provided that controls
        how additional space is assigned to the rows and columns. So for
        instance you can specify that when the user enlarges a dialog the text
        fields grow, but the labels remain their size.
      </p>
      <p>
        Based on this fundamental and mighty layout manager class there are
        some other useful layout manager implementations:
        <ul>
          <li><code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/layout/BorderLayout.html">
          BorderLayout</a></code> is a slightly more powerful implementation of
          AWT's layout manager with the same name. Its main purpose is to
          bring this easy yet convenient layouting scheme to other GUI toolkits
          that do not support it (SWT for instance).</li>
          <li><code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/layout/ButtonLayout.html">
          ButtonLayout</a></code> is well suited for creating bars that hold
          the buttons (e.g. <em>Close</em>, <em>Cancel</em>, <em>Apply</em>) of
          a dialog. It ensures that all buttons have the same size and the
          spaces between the buttons are equal. The button bar can be aligned to
          the left, the right, or centered.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Actions and Command Objects">
      <p>
        So by now you have a generic <code>Application</code> object and can
        create a GUI using the <em>GUI builder</em>. A question remains: what
        about the application's logic?
      </p>
      <p>
        JGUIraffe makes heavy use of the <em>Action</em> concept also known from
        other GUI toolkits like Swing or SWT. An action contains a piece of code
        that gets executed when a GUI control was triggered by the user.
        Usually actions are associated with menu items or toolbar buttons,
        i.e. the typical controls for representing commands to be executed.
      </p>
      <p>
        The actions supported by the JGUIraffe library can be defined in the
        XML scripts, from which the GUI is generated. In addition to more
        graphical properties like a name, a tooltip, or an icon (which are used
        to define the controls the action is associated with), an action must be
        assigned a <em>task</em> object. This is a normal Java object that
        implements the <code>Runnable</code> interface (which should be familar
        to everybody who has ever started a thread). The task can directly be
        defined in the XML file using the <em>dependency injection framework</em>
        mentioned above. So a typical approach would be to define your
        application's logic in a set of task classes and associate instances of
        these classes with actions, which are itself associated with GUI
        controls.
      </p>
      <p>
        One problem with GUI oriented Java applications are long running tasks.
        If an action is triggered, its code is typically executed on the same
        thread that is also responsible for maintaining the GUI. So if the
        the action's task needs a while to finish, for this time the GUI will
        be blocked.
      </p>
      <p>
        As a solution to this problem JGUIraffe introduces so called
        <em>Command Objects</em>. Command objects are an implementation of the
        popular GoF <em>Command</em> pattern. They are similar to an action's
        task in that they define a single method for executing the command.
        A command object can be passed to the central <code>Application</code>
        object. This object will take care that the command object is executed
        in a background thread, so the GUI will stay responsive. If the
        command object needs to update the GUI after it has run, it can do so
        by placing the corresponding code in a special method; this method
        will be executed on the special GUI thread, which will ensure proper
        synchronization.
      </p>
      <p>
        To combine the concept of actions with the concept of command objects
        there is a special action task class called
        <code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/CommandActionTask.html">
        CommandActionTask</a></code>. Instances of this class can be used as
        tasks for actions. They hold a reference to a command object. When
        they are invoked (because the associated action was triggered by the
        user) they pass their command object to the central
        <code>Application</code> object so that it is executed in a background
        thread. <code>CommandActionTask</code> objects can be fully defined in
        GUI builder XML files.
      </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Working with Forms">
      <p>
        GUI centric applications typically use dialogs or forms for gathering
        input data from their users. Creating and managing such a form is a
        tedious task in standard Java programming: When the form's GUI has been
        set up the developer has to ensure that all input fields are
        correctly populated with data from the application's model. This may
        involve some transformations of data types, e.g. if a date value is to
        be entered in a text field, it must be converted into a proper text
        format.
      </p>
      <p>
        After the user has completed the input task and pressed the
        &quot;OK&quot; button the entered values have to be checked if they
        are valid. For instance the date the user might have entered into a
        field might not exist or be syntactically wrong. When all fields are
        valid their values must be written back into the application's model
        for further processing, e.g. for storing in a database. Here again
        data transformations may happen (of course the date object should be
        stored as a <code>java.util.Date</code> rather than plain text).
      </p>
      <p>
        If all these tasks have to be performed manually, each form requires a
        fair amount of boiler-plate code. To simplify the management of forms
        the JGUIraffe library provides the concept of <em>Form</em> objects. A
        form is represented by an instance of the
        <code><a href="apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/forms/Form.html">Form</a></code>
        class. Instances of this class store all the fields the form contains
        and allow easy access to their current values.
      </p>
      <p>
        Each field of a form can be associated with a couple of helper objects,
        which are responsible for correctly managing the field's data. These
        are the following:
        <ul>
          <li>A <em>write transformer</em>: This object is responsible for
          performing necessary transformations of the field's native data so
          that it can be edited using a specific GUI element. In our example
          with the date field the write transformer would convert the date
          value to a string that can be assigned to a standard text field.</li>
          <li>A <em>read transformer</em>: A read transformer does the
          opposite transformation than a write transformer. It is invoked when
          the form's data is to be extracted from the GUI input elements. In
          the case of a date field the user's input must be converted from text
          to date again.</li>
          <li>A <em>field level validator</em>: The task of this object is to
          check whether the data the user has entered in an input element is
          syntactically correct. So for instance for date fields it must be
          checked if the string the user has typed into a text field does
          indeed represent an existing date value.</li>
          <li>A <em>form level validator</em>: After syntatic checks of all of
          the form's input elements have been successfull an additional check
          on the semantic level can be performed. This is an optional second
          validation phase, in which for instance relations between multiple
          input elements can be evaluated. So it could be checked whether the
          value in the field <em>date of delivery</em> lies at least a week in
          the future if the <em>express delivery</em> checkbox is unchecked.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        A form object has methods for reading and writing form data that
        automatically invoke these helper objects -- if they are defined -- at
        the correct points in time. As source and destination of form data an
        arbitrary Java bean can be used. The bean's properties are mapped to
        form fields based on their name. This makes handling of forms quite
        convenient. Let's say for example we have a form for editing the data
        of a customer. Then we can do the following steps:
        <ol>
          <li>We obtain the bean that represents the customer to be edited. In
          a typical application this would be loaded from a database.</li>
          <li>On our form object we call the <code>initFields()</code> method
          and pass in the customer bean. This will cause all input fields that
          can be matched to properties of the bean to be automatically
          populated.</li>
          <li>When the user hits the &quot;OK&quot; button the
          <code>validateFields()</code> method is to be called on the form.
          This method returns information about all fields that contain
          invalid data. If there are such fields, we can display a message
          box with appropriate information and hints.</li>
          <li>If all fields are valid, we call the <code>readFields()</code>
          method and again pass in the customer bean. This will cause the
          current values of the input fields to be written back to the bean.
          We could then update the bean in the database.</li>
        </ol>
      </p>
      <p>
        And now comes the best part: such a form object can be automatically
        created for you! Every time you use the <em>GUI builder</em> (see
        above) for generating a GUI a <code>Form</code> object is automatically
        constructed and for each processed input element a field object is
        added. In the XML document that controls the GUI building process
        special tags can be used for defining transformers and validators for
        the input elements. So you get a fully initialized form object for free.
      </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
