<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--

    Copyright 2006-2012 The JGUIraffe Team.

    Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License")
    you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
    You may obtain a copy of the License at

        http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.

-->
<!-- $Id: application.xml 212 2012-07-14 15:22:35Z oheger $ -->

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Application</title>
  <author email="oheger@users.sourceforge.net">Oliver Heger</author>
 </properties>

<body>
  <section name="The central Application class">
  <p>
    Each <em>JGUIraffe</em> application is represented by an object derived
    from the central
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
    Application</a></code> class. <code>Application</code> provides fundamental
    services that can be used by concrete applications, e.g. life-cycle events,
    configuration support, handling of a main window, and many more. It also
    serves as the entry point in the application, i.e. it provides a
    <code>main()</code> method that can directly be used.
  </p>
  <p>
    Starting an application is a complex operation. A lot of initialization
    steps have to be performed until the main window is displayed, and the
    application is ready for user interaction. This section describes these
    steps and discusses hooks for customization.
  </p>
  <p>
    After that we discuss what happens when an application terminates.
  </p>

  <subsection name="Initializations at startup">
  <p>
    The main entry point into a JGUIraffe application is the static
    <code>startup()</code> method of
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
    Application</a></code>. This method is called with the <code>Application</code>
    instance to launch. This can either be a direct instance of the
    <code>Application</code> class or of a derived class.
    <code>Application</code> is fully functional and can be used out of the box.
    In this case there is no need to define a custom <code>main()</code> method;
    the one provided by <code>Application</code> can be used directly.
    Only if special customization is required, a sub class can be created, which
    overrides some of the hook methods.
  </p>
  <p>
    During the startup phase the following initializations are performed (in
    this order):
    <ul>
      <li>The location of the main configuration file of the application is
      determined. For this purpose system properties are evaluated.</li>
      <li>A hook method for command line processing is invoked.</li>
      <li>The main configuration file of the application is read.</li>
      <li>The <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/BeanBuilderFactory.html">
      BeanBuilderFactory</a></code> to be used by the application is created
      from the configuration and installed.</li>
      <li>The global <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/BeanContext.html">
      BeanContext</a></code> of the application is created and initialized. It
      is populated with the default bean definitions shipped with the framework.</li>
      <li>The global <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/ClassLoaderProvider.html">
      ClassLoaderProvider</a></code> is created.</li>
      <li>Further bean definition files that can be specified in the main
      configuration file are read.</li>
      <li>The <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/ApplicationContext.html">
      ApplicationContext</a></code> and its helper objects are created from the
      global <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/BeanContext.html">
      BeanContext</a></code>.</li>
      <li>The main builder script defining the UI of the application is
      determined from the configuration. If it is specified, it is processed,
      and the main application window is created from it. However, this is
      optional. An application may choose not to define its main window this
      way.</li>
      <li>If a main window is defined, it is initialized. This includes setting
      its position and size to the values stored at the last execution of the
      application.</li>
      <li>The applications's <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/cmd/CommandQueue.html">
      CommandQueue</a></code> is created and installed.</li>
      <li>If a main window is defined, it is displayed now.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Hooks">
  <p>
    The initialization steps outlined above are performed by well-defined methods
    of the <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/Application.html">
    Application</a></code> class. In many cases it is possible to hook into
    the initialization process by overriding corresponding methods. This
    section discusses the methods that can be used as hooks and provides further
    information about the initialization procedure.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Determining the main configuration file</strong><br/>
      A JGUIraffe application uses the <a href="http://commons.apache.org/configuration">
      Commons Configuration</a> library for reading configuration data. It
      expects the configuration data to be defined in a so-called
      <em>configuration definition file</em>, which is an XML document
      referring to an arbitrary number of configuration files (or other
      configuration sources). The name of this configuration definition file
      must be known in order to read it. It can be specified in the following
      ways:
      <ul>
        <li>As resource name: In this case it will be searched in the class
        path. This is appropriate, for instance, if the whole configuration can
        be shipped with the application in a jar archive.</li>
        <li>As URL: Using this approach an arbitrary URL to the configuration
        file can be specified, e.g. pointing to a file or to a web server.</li>
      </ul>
      The <code>Application</code> class has the properties <code>configResourceName</code>
      and <code>configURL</code> for specifying the location of the configuration
      file either as resource name or as URL. They can be set before the
      <code>Application</code> to be started is passed to the static
      <code>startup()</code> method. If they are not set, the framework reads
      the values of the following system properties:
      <ul>
        <li><code>net.sf.jguiraffe.configName</code> for obtaining the resource
        name of the configuration file or</li>
        <li><code>net.sf.jguiraffe.configURL</code> for obtaining the URL
        pointing to the configuration file.</li>
      </ul>
      If neither the properties of the <code>Application</code> instance nor the
      system properties are defined, the framework uses the default name
      <em>config.xml</em> and tries to load the file from the class path.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Command line processing</strong><br/>
      For this purpose the <code>processCommandLine(String[] args)</code> method
      is invoked. The default implementation of this method is empty. A class
      derived from <code>Application</code> can override this method to perform
      arbitrary evaluations of the command line arguments passed to the
      application at startup.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Reading the configuration</strong><br/>
      The application's configuration file is actually read by the
      <code>createConfiguration()</code> method. An application that needs a
      completely different mechanism of defining the location of the configuration
      file can override this method. The <code>HierarchicalConfiguration</code>
      object returned by this method will become the global configuration of
      this application.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Setting up the <code>BeanBuilderFactory</code></strong><br/>
      The <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/BeanBuilderFactory.html">
      BeanBuilderFactory</a></code> is needed for obtaining a reference to the
      <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/builder/BeanBuilder.html">
      BeanBuilder</a></code>, i.e. the component that processes bean definition
      files. Because the <code>BeanBuilderFactory</code> cannot be specified in
      bean definition file itself, it is obtained from the application's
      configuration. An application may specify a custom factory class; a
      fragment of a configuration file which does exactly this could look as
      follows:
            <source><![CDATA[
<config>
  <framework>
    <builder>
      <beanBuilderFactory config-class="my.bean.FactoryClass">
      </beanBuilderFactory>
      ...
    </builder>
    ...
  </framework>
  ...
         ]]></source>
         However, using a custom bean builder factory should only be necessary
         for applications with very specific requirements.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Setting up the <code>BeanContext</code></strong><br/>
      With the <code>BeanBuilderFactory</code> up and running the bean definition
      files can now be processed and a <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/BeanContext.html">
      BeanContext</a></code> allowing access to the beans defined there can be
      created. At first a bean definition file with default declarations for
      fundamental service beans is read. This file is shipped with the framework
      and produces a default configuration. It is possible to override these
      default beans with custom ones, which is explained in a few minutes.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Setting up the <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code></strong><br/>
    A <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/di/ClassLoaderProvider.html">
    ClassLoaderProvider</a></code> plays an important role in a complex
    application setup using multiple class loaders: In bean definition files
    the classes of the beans to be created are defined using their fully
    qualified names. When the beans are actually created these names have to
    be resolved to concrete <code>Class</code> objects. For each bean it is
    possible to specify a concrete <code>ClassLoader</code> to be used for this
    purpose. A <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> is a kind of registry for
    class loaders. Class loaders can be registered under a symbolic name. In
    bean declarations these symbolic names can be used again for referring to
    a specific class loader. If no name for a class loader is provided in a bean
    definition, the default class loader is used. For the most desktop
    applications this default should be appropriate.
  </p>
  <p>
    If an enhanced class loader setup is required, the
    <code>initClassLoaderProvider()</code> method can be overriden. This
    method is passed the default <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> object, which
    was created from the default bean definitions. A custom implementation of
    this method can register application-specific class loaders at the passed
    in provider, or, alternatively, create a completely different
    <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> - the object returned from this method will
    become the global <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> used by all bean builder
    operations.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Custom bean definitions</strong><br/>
    After the creation of the <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code> the framework
    searches the configuration for additional bean definitions to be read. Per
    default, a special section of the application's configuration file is
    evaluated for determining the names of additional bean definition files.
    The following example shows a fragment of a configuration file that defines
    additional bean definition files:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
<config>
  <framework>
    <builder>
      <beandefinitions>
        <beandefinition>classpath:/jelly_scripts/applicationbeans.jelly</beandefinition>
        <beandefinition>url:http://www.myserver.com/config.jelly</beandefinition>
      </beandefinitions>
      ...
  ]]></source>
  <p>
    Under <code>&lt;beandefinitions&gt;</code> an arbitrary number of
    <code>&lt;beandefinition&gt;</code> elements can occur. Each specifies the
    name of a bean definition file. Bean definition files define service beans
    that are available for the application. We will provide more information
    about this topic when we discuss <a href="dibuilder.html">the dependency
    injection builder</a> in a later chapter. Here we just focus on the way
    such bean definitions can be passed to the application.
  </p>
  <p>
    The easiest way of adding further bean definitions is to list the files to
    be processed in this section in the configuration file. If an application
    needs more flexibility, it can override the <code>findBeanDefinitions()</code>
    method. This method returns a collection of
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/locators/Locator.html">Locator
    </a></code> objects pointing to the bean definitions to be processed. The
    base implementation of the <code>findBeanDefinitions()</code> method uses
    an instance of the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/locators/LocatorConverter.html">
    LocatorConverter</a></code> class to transform textual representations to
    concrete <code>Locator</code> implementations. Such textual representations
    start with a prefix (e.g. <em>classpath:</em> or <em>url:</em>) followed by
    the actual data of the <code>Locator</code>. Refer to the documentation of
    the <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/locators/LocatorConverter.html">
    LocatorConverter</a></code> class for more details.
  </p>
  <p>
    Providing custom bean definitions is a powerful means of defining the
    application's behavior. It is good practice to define central services of
    the application as beans, which can be accessed by all application
    components acting as clients of these services. It is also possible to
    override any or all of the default beans defined by the framework. To do
    this, just define a bean with the same name as a standard bean in an
    additional bean definition file. The new bean will replace the standard bean.
    This also works if the bean that was replaced is referenced by other
    standard beans: these beans will also use the new bean. More information
    about standard beans can be found in the sub section
    <a href="dibuilder.html#standard_beans">Application standard beans</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Setting up the <code>ApplicationContext</code></strong><br/>
    Each application is associated with a single instance of the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/ApplicationContext.html">
    ApplicationContext</a></code> class. This instance especially holds references
    to some fundamental service objects (like the resource manager, the
    configuration, or the GUI synchronizer), and provides some important
    functionality often needed by applications.
  </p>
  <p>
    Creation of the <code>ApplicationContext</code> is done by the
    <code>createApplicationContext()</code>. The default implementation of
    <code>createApplicationContext()</code> performs some of the initializations
    already discussed (reading the configuration, setting up the
    <code>BeanContext</code> and the <code>ClassLoaderProvider</code>, processing
    additional bean definition files). Finally, it has a fully initialized
    <code>BeanContext</code>. From this context the application context is
    obtained. So for applications that want to replace the standard
    <code>ApplicationContext</code> by a custom implementation, the easiest way
    is to override the bean definition for the application context bean. To do
    this a bean with the name <em>jguiraffe.applicationContext</em> has to be
    defined in an additional bean definition file.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Initializing the main window</strong><br/>
    An important feature of the JGUIraffe library is its support for builder
    scripts defining UI elements. So it is naturally that this feature is also
    used here for defining the application's main GUI. Initialization of the
    GUI is performed by the <code>initGUI()</code> method. The default
    implementation obtains the name of the builder script with the GUI
    definition from the main configuration file. It can be defined there as in
    the following example:
  </p>
  <source><![CDATA[
<config>
  <framework>
    <builder>
      <mainScript>/jelly_scripts/mainWindow.jelly</mainScript>
      ...
  ]]></source>
  <p>
    If the <code>mainScript</code> property is defined, the referenced builder
    is load from the class path and executed. If this results in a window,
    <code>setMainWindow()</code> is called on the <code>ApplicationContext</code>
    to install the application's main window. Applications that want to use a
    different way of defining their GUI can override <code>initGUI()</code>.
    It does not matter how the actually create their main window. All they have
    to do is calling <code>setMainWindow()</code> to register the main window
    with the application context.
  </p>
  <p>
    <strong>Setting up the <code>CommandQueue</code></strong><br/>
    Longer-running tasks must not be run on the event dispatch thread because
    otherwise the GUI will block. JGUIraffe uses an object implementing the
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/cmd/CommandQueue.html">
    CommandQueue</a></code> interface for offering support for background tasks.
    The concrete implementation of this interface is created by the
    <code>createCommandQueue()</code> method. The default implementation just
    obtains the queue object from the global <code>BeanContext</code>.
  </p>
  <p>
    It should rarely be necessary to replace the <code>CommandQueue</code>
    implementation. In such cases, the best was is to override the
    <em>jguiraffe.commandQueue</em> bean definition. Overriding
    <code>createCommandQueue()</code> may make sense, for instance, if an
    application wants to register specific listeners at the queue; these
    listeners can receive notifications e.g. when commands are executed or if
    the queue changes from the idle to the busy state or vice versa.
  </p>
  <p>
    So far the most important hook methods defined by the <code>Application</code>
    class. Note that for all of these methods fully functional default
    implementations are provided, which should be sufficient in many cases.
    Only if specific behavior is required, some of these methods can be
    overridden.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Shutdown">
  <p>
    The <code>Application</code> class is responsible for the whole life-cycle
    of the application it represents. Consequently, it also provides methods
    for terminating the application: the <code>shutdown()</code> methods.
  </p>
  <p>
    There are two overloaded variants of the <code>shutdown()</code> method: one
    is interactive, the other is not. Interactive in this context means that the
    method first checks whether it is safe to exit the application now and
    prompts the user if necessary. A <em>JGUIraffe</em> application can start
    long-running tasks in a background thread. It is possible that such a
    background task is still running when the user decides to exit the
    application (e.g. by clicking the close icon of the main window). In this
    case the <code>shutdown()</code> method displays a message box with a
    corresponding warning and asks whether the user really wants to exit the
    application. Only if the user confirms this message box, the shutdown
    sequence continues. (For more information about background tasks refer to
    the <a href="commands.html">Commands</a> section.)
  </p>
  <p>
    The content of the message to be displayed to the user if there are still
    background threads running is determined by the arguments passed to the
    <code>shutdown()</code> method. Here a resource ID for the caption and one
    for the actual message can be specified. The sub section
    <a href="resources.html#Convenience_methods">Convenience methods</a> provides
    more information about these resource IDs.
  </p>
  <p>
    The overloaded <code>shutdown()</code> method does not take any arguments.
    It does not check whether background tasks are running. So this step of the
    shutdown sequence is skipped.
  </p>
  <p>
    If there are no more background tasks or the user decided to exit anyway,
    <code>Application</code> processes all registered <em>shutdown
    listeners</em>. At any time of the lifetime of the central
    <code>Application</code> object before <code>shutdown()</code> is called
    event listeners of type
    <code><a href="../apidocs/net/sf/jguiraffe/gui/app/ApplicationShutdownListener.html">
    ApplicationShutdownListener</a></code> can be registered by calling the
    <code>addShutdownListener()</code> method. The
    <code>ApplicationShutdownListener</code> interface defines two methods:
    <ul>
    <li><code>canShutdown()</code> is invoked first and checks whether the
    application can shutdown now. If an <code>ApplicationShutdownListener</code>
    implementation returns <b>false</b>, the shutdown sequence is aborted. A use
    case for this method could be to check whether there are still unsafed
    changes and prompt the user whether the application should really exit. If
    the user denies this, the listener can abort the operation. (The same could
    also be achieved by registering a listener at the application's main window.)
    </li>
    <li>Only if all registered <code>ApplicationShutdownListener</code> objects
    have returned <b>true</b> in their <code>canShutdown()</code> method, the
    second method, <code>shutdown()</code>, is invoked on all listeners. This
    method notifies the listeners that the application is actually going to
    exit. An implementation could for instance perform some cleanup or free
    resources used by the application.</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    In the next phase the protected <code>onShutdown()</code> method of
    <code>Application</code> is called. The base implementation of this method
    takes care that the <em>user configuration</em> is stored correctly. The
    user configuration is a configuration object managed by the application which
    can be populated with arbitrary data. Here also the position and the size of
    the main window are stored so that they can be restored when the application
    starts the next time. The user configuration is stored in the user's home
    directory. So if the application is started by different users, they all
    have their own user configuration.
  </p>
  <p>
    After that some internal cleanup is performed. Resources obtained during the
    execution of the builder scripts executed in the initialization phase
    are released. Eventually the <code>exitApplication()</code> method is
    invoked which calls <code>System.exit()</code> and terminates the
    application.
  </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Exit handlers">
  <p>
    Well, in fact calling <code>System.exit()</code> is just the default
    behavior at the end of a successful shutdown operation. There may be
    scenarios in which it is not desired to terminate the whole Java virtual
    machine, e.g. when the application is running in a managed environment.
    For such cases <code>Application</code> allows setting a so-called
    <em>exit handler</em>.
  </p>
  <p>
    An exit handler simply has to implement the <code>Runnable</code>
    interface. It can be passed to the <code>setExitHandler()</code> method of
    <code>Application</code>. At the end of a shutdown operation - if there is
    no veto from a shutdown listener - the exit handler is invoked. This is
    the last operation performed by the <code>Application</code> object. It is
    then in the responsibility of the concrete exit handler implementation to
    actually complete the shutdown. As was already mentioned, the default exit
    handler calls <code>System.exit()</code>. If you need other shutdown logic,
    create a <code>Runnable</code> object implementing the desired behavior and
    pass it to <code>Application</code>'s <code>setExitHandler()</code> method.
  </p>
  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>

</document>